Finding Aid for the Philip Durham Papers LSC.0824
UCLA Library Special Collections
Philip Durham papers
1956-1970
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.0824
1 unknown (1 oversize boxes)
Philip Durham (1912-1977) was a professor of American literature at UCLA (1953-1976), Fulbright professor of American literature at the University of Helsinki(1955-56) and the author of several books. The collection consists of manuscripts, proof sheets, correspondence, books (many edited or with a forward by Durham), magazine articles, and research materials.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Philip Durham, 1960-1966.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9912178923606533
Biography
Durham was born February 7, 1912 in Portland, Oregon; BS, Linfield College, 1935; MA, Claremont Graduate School, 1946; Ph.D, Northwestern University, 1949; member of faculty, Elmhurst College, 1949-51; instructor (1953-55), assistant professor (1955-61), associate professor (1961-66), professor (1966-76), and professor emeritus (1976-77), UCLA; Department of English; Fulbright professor of American literature, University of Helsinki, 1955-56; author of several books, including: American Fiction in Finland (with Tauno F. Mustanoja, 1960), Down these Mean Streets a Man Must Go: Raymond Chandler's Knight (1963), The Negro Cowboys (with Everett Jones, 1965), and The Western Story: Fact, Fiction, and Myth (1975); died March 27, 1977.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of manuscripts and proof sheets for Philip Durham's The Negro Cowboys, and Down These Mean Streets a Man Must Go. Manuscripts also include American Fiction in Finland, The lost cowboy (an article), and The Adventures of the Negro Cowboys. The collection also contains correspondence, books (many edited or with a forward by Durham), magazine articles, and research materials.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
American Fiction in Finland (Boxes 1,15).
Down these Mean Streets a Man Must Go: Raymond Chandler's Knight (Boxes 1,2,4).
Correspondence (Boxes 1-3,5,7,10).
Adventures of the Negro Cowboys (Box 4).
The Negro Cowboys (Boxes 5-6,8-12).
Killer in the Rain; Deadwood Dick on Deck (Box 7).
Ex libris Philip Durham (Boxes 13-15).
Topical office files (Boxes 15-16).
Research material and card index on western life (Box 17).
African American cowboys -- Research.; Manuscripts for publication; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; University of California, Los Angeles--Faculty; Chandler, Raymond; Durham, Philip--Archives.
- Durham, Philip, 1912-. American Fiction in Finland. An essay and bibliography by Philip Durham and Tauno F. Mustanoja. Helsinki: Societe Neophilologique, 1960.; 191pp. Page proofs with holograph corrections in pencil. (Box 1)
- --- ---- Another copy., Proof sheets with holograph corrections in pencil. (Box 1)
- --- ---- Another copy., Mint copy of the book as issued. (Box 1)
- --- Folder of correspondence relating to American Fiction in Finland. (Box 1)
- --- Down These Mean Streets a Man Must Go: Raymond Chandler's Knight. Los Angeles, ca. Chapel Hill: The University of North Carolina Press, 1962. 1963.; 177, 18 leaves. Typescript with corrections (printer's copy). (Box 1)
- --- ---- Another copy., Proof sheets with corrections. (Box 1)
- --- ---- Another copy., Page proofs with corrections. (Box 1)
- --- Ephemera relating to Down These Mean Streets a Man Must Go: Raymond Chandler's Knight. (Box 1)
- --- ---- Another copy. Noted Author's indexing set., Page proofs with corrections. (Box 2)
- --- Folder of miscellaneous notes, drafts, and other material comprising part of the research for Down These Mean Streets a Man Must Go: Raymond Chandler's Knight., ca. 200 items. Included are holograph and typescript notes, lists, copies of various reviews of Chandler's work, and corrected typescript drafts. The material is not arranged in any particular order. (Box 2)
- --- Folder of excerpts of correspondence from Raymond Chandler to James Sandoe, sent to Philip Durham by Dorothy Gardiner, in relation to research for Down These Mean Streets a Man Must Go: Raymond Chandler's Knight. Attached is a typescript note from Dorothy Gardiner to Philip Durham., Typescript copies, mostly carbon. 22 leaves. (Box 2)
- --- One envelope of cards comprising part of Philip Durham's research for Down These Mean Streets a Man Must Go: Raymond Chandler's Knight., Holograph notes on ca. 120 cards. (Box 2)
- --- Folder of correspondence relating to Down These Mean Streets a Man Must Go: Raymond Chandler's Knight. (Box 2)
- --- A selected checklist. n.p., ). This list appears in Down These Mean Streets a Man Must Go: Raymond Chandler's Knight. Carbon copy also included., 32 leaves. Typescript. (Box 2)
- Correspondence and ephemera relating to the Mystery Writers of America. New York, ca., 1956-.; Typescript, mimeograph and printed, arranged in manilla folders. (Box 3)
- --- Down These Mean Streets a Man Must Go: Raymond Chandler's Knight., Typescript draft with many corrections and notations. The leaves are not arranged in any particular order. (Box 4)
- --- Down These Mean Streets a Man Must Go: Raymond Chandler's Knight. One copy noted Index first rough copy (with notes)., Typescript (some carbon leaves) with many corrections. Included are 2 copies of the preface, and 2 copies of the index. (Box 4)
  General note
  A selected checklist, and works consulted are not included.
- --- ---- Another copy. This copy does not include the index., Typescript (carbon) with many corrections and a few holograph leaves near the end. (Box 4)
- --- The Adventures of the Negro Cowboys. Children's version of The Negro Cowboys. New York: Dodd, Mead, 1966.; 152 leaves. Typescript (carbon) with a few corrections. (Box 4)
- --- ---- New York: Dodd, Mead, 1966.; 46 leaves. Galleys. (Box 4)
- --- The Lost Cowboy. Los Angeles, Apparently written for a journal concerning The Negro Cowboys., 1965.; 9 leaves. Typescript. (Box 5)
- --- The Negro Cowboys. Los Angeles, ca. New York: Dodd, Mead, 1965., ca. 400 leaves. Typescript (photocopy). (Box 5)
- --- Folder of notes relating to The Negro Cowboys., Typescript and holograph leaves. (Box 5)
- --- Folder of notes, correspondence, and ephemera relating to The Negro Cowboys., Typescript and holograph leaves. (Box 5)
- --- Folder of notes and ephemera relating to The Negro Cowboys., Holograph. Holograph leaves. (Box 5)
- Group of materials for the exhibit on the Negro cowboy at the University Research Library, UCLA. (Box 5)
- --- Notes and ephemera relating to The Negro Cowboys., Mostly typescript on cards with some holograph notes. (Box 6)
- --- Correspondence with Hamish Hamilton relating to Raymond Chandler's Killer in the Rain. London: Hamish Hamilton, 1964. (Box 7)
- --- Introduction to Killer in the Rain by Raymond Chandler, Los Angeles, 1964.; 9 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. Also carbon and photocopy copies. (Box 7)
- Seth Jones by Edward S. Ellis and Deadwood Dick on Deck by Edward L. Wheeler. Edited by Philip Durham. Published by Odyssey, n.p., 1966.; 166, 156 leaves. Typescript (carbon) in 2 folders. (Box 7)
- --- Seth Jones and Deadwood Dick on Deck. Published by Odyssey, n.p., 1966.; 74 leaves. Galleys. (Box 7)
- Work sheets relating to The Negro Cowboys., 3 folders. Typescript and holograph sheets with corrections. (Box 8)
- Index for The Negro Cowboys., Typescript and holograph cards. (Box 9)
- Work sheets relating to The Negro Cowboys., Photocopy and holograph sheets with corrections. (Box 9)
- Correspondence, notes, and ephemera relating to The Negro Cowboys. (Box 10)
- Durham, Philip. The Negro Cowboys. Los Angeles, ca., 1965.; ca. 300 leaves. photocopy copy with holograph corrections. (Box 10)
- --- ----. Rough draft., Typescript with holograph corrections from which a photocopy copy was made. (Box 10)
- --- ----. Another copy., 266 leaves. photocopy with holograph corrections. (Box 11)
- --- ----. Another copy with bibliography., ca. 400 leaves. photocopy. (Box 11)
- Bibliography for The Negro Cowboys., 27 leaves. photocopy. (Box 11)
- Durham, Philip. The Negro Cowboys. Los Angeles, ca., 1965.; ca. 400 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 12)
- --- ----., 92 leaves. Galleys. (Box 12)
- --- ----., Galleys and page proofs. (Box 12)
- --- ----., Incomplete copy.ca. 350 leaves. Verifax. (Box 11)
- Photographs used for The Negro Cowboys., 11 items. Glossy print. (Box 11)
- Folder of material relating to The Negro Cowboys, collected by Lillian J. Hayes of UCLA's Fine Arts Productions & Public Lectures. (Box 12)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contents: posters, clippings, brochures, radio scripts, and some correspondence.
- Ex libris Philip Durham.
  - -Schorer, Mark, et al. Harbrace College Reader. New York: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Incorporated, c. 1972.; 2 copies. 608pp. (Box 13)
    Durham was one of the editors.
  - -Garther, Marion, et al. Bold Journeys. London: The MacMillan Company, c. 1970.; 534pp. (Box 13)
    Winners of the West by Philip Durham and Everett L. Jones, p.142.
  - -Henry, Will, pseudonym. Chiricahua. Philadelphia and New York: J.B. Lippincott Company, c. 1972.; Uncorrected page proofs. 262pp. (Box 13)
  - -Schorer, Mark, et al. Harbrace College Reader. New York/Burlingame: Harcourt, Brace & World, Incorporated, c. 1964.; 551pp. (Box 13)
  - -Schorer, Mark, et al. Harbrace College Reader. New York: Harcourt, Brace and Company, c. 1959.; 620pp. (Box 13)
  - -Schorer, Mark, et al. Harbrace College Reader. New York/Chicago, San Francisco/Atlanta: Harcourt, Brace & World, Incorporated, c. 1968.; 642pp. (Box 13)
  - -Chandler, Raymond. Killer in the Rain. New York: Pocket Books, Incorporated, c. 1965.; 398pp. (Box 13)
    Introduction by Philip Durham.
  - -Chandler, Raymond. Killer in the Rain. Harmondsworth, England: Penguin Books, c. 1966.; 429pp. (Box 13)
  - -Chandler, Raymond. Killer in the Rain. London: Hamish Hamilton, c. 1964., 332pp. (Box 13)
  - -Chandler, Raymond. Killer in the Rain. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, c. 1964.; 394pp. (Box 14)
  - -Chandler, Raymond. Killer in the Rain. London: Hamish Hamilton, c. 1964.; 332pp. (Box 14)
  - -Durham, Philip, et al. The Adventures of the Negro Cowboys. New York/Toronto/London, Bantam Books, c. 1969. (Box 14)
  - -Durham, Philip, et al. The Adventures of the Negro Cowboys. New York: Dodd, Mead & Company, c. 1966.; 143pp. (Box 14)
  - -Durham, Philip. Down these Mean Streets a Man Must Go. Chapel Hill: The University of North Carolina Press, c. 1963.; 173pp. (Box 14)
  - -Chandler, Raymond. Down these Mean Streets a Man Must Go. Chapel Hill: The University of North Carolina Press, c. 1963.; 173pp. Paperback. (Box 14)
  - -Durham, Philip, et al. American Fiction in Finland. Helsinki: Société Néophilologique, c. 1960.; 202pp. (Box 14)
  - -Wister, Owen. The Virginian. A Horseman of the Plains. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, c. 1968.; 304pp. Paperback. (Box 14)
    Edited and with an introduction by Philip Durham.
  - -Wister, Owen. The Virginian. A Horseman of the Plains. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, c. 1968.; 304pp. (Box 14)
    Edited with an introduction by Philip Durham.
  - -Durham, Philip, et al. The Negro Cowboys. New York: Dood, Mead & Company, c. 1965.; 278pp. (Box 14)
  - -Durham, Philip, et al. The Frontier in American Literature. New York: The Odyssey Press, c. 1969.; 393pp. (Box 14)
  - -Ellis, Edward S. Seth Jones and Deadwood Dick on Deck [by] Edward L. Wheeler. New York: The Odyssey Press, Incorporated, c. 1966.; 188pp. (Box 14)
    Edited by Philip Durham.
  - -Durham, Philip, et al. American Fiction in Finland. Helsinki: Société Néophilologique, c. 1960.; 202pp. Paperback. (Box 15)
  - -Durham, Philip. Prelude to the Constable Edition of Melville. Reprinted from The Huntington Library Quarterly. vol.21, no.3 ()., May 1958 (Box 15)
  - -Durham, Philip. The Lost Cowboy, The Midwest Journal: a Magazine of Research & Creative Writing. vol.7, no.2 ()., Summer 1955; pp.176-182. (Box 15)
  - -Durham, Philip. A General Classification of 1,531 Dime Novels, reprinted from The Huntington Library Quarterly. vol.17, no.3 ()., May 1954; pp.287-291. 2 copies. (Box 15)
  - -Durham, Philip. Dime novels: An American Heritage, The Western Humanities Review. vol.9, no.1 (Winter 1954-55)., pp.33-43. With reprint. (Box 15)
  - -Durham, Philip. The Negro Cowboy, American Quarterly. vol.7, no.3 ()., Fall 1955; pp.291-301. With extra pages, 291-301. (Box 15)
  - -Durham, Philip. The Lost Cowboy, The Midwest Journal. vol.7, no.2 ()., Summer 1955; pp.176-182. (Box 15)
  - -Durham, Philip. The Cowboy and the Myth Makers, Journal of Popular Culture. vol.1, no.1 ()., Summer 1967; pp.58-62. (Box 15)
  - -Hagemann, E.R. and Durham, Philip C. James M. Cain, 1922-1958: A Selected Checklist, Bulletin of Bibliography. vol.23, no.3 /214 ()., September-December 1960; pp.57-61. (Box 15)
  - -Durham, Philip. Riders of the Plains, Neuphilologische Mitteilungen. vol.58, no.1 ()., 1957; pp.22-38. With reprint. (Box 15)
  - -Durham, Philip. The Desperado as Hero, The Arkansas Historical Quarterly. vol.14, no.4 ()., Winter 1955; pp.340-358. (Box 15)
  - -Durham, Philip. The Beat Literature, The UCLA Alumni Magazine. vol.34, no.8 ()., May-June 1960; pp.9-10. (Box 15)
  - -Instructor's Manual for Harbrace College Reader. Fifth edition and advertisement. (Box 15)
  - -Durham, Philip, et al. The West: From Fact to Myth. Catalogue of an exhibit in the UCLA Library., September 20-October 24, 1967. (Box 15)
  - -The Boys in the Black Mask. An exhibit in the UCLA Library, January 6-February 10, 1961.; 2 copies. (Box 15)
  - -Science Research Associates. (Box 15)
    - Old Two Toes. (Box 15)
    - The Remarkable Bill Pickett. (Box 15)
- Correspondence. (Box 15)
  - -Wilson, Dave., January 30, 1957.; 1 postcard. (Box 15)
- Manuscript Material. (Box 15)
  - -American Writing in Finland. Photocopy., 14 leaves. (Box 15)
- Additions, August 1982
  - Files from Philip Durham's office, listed by folder title. (Box 15)
    - -Academic disciplines. Folklore and mythology (VI-E). (Box 15)
    - -Academic disciplines. Philosophy (VI-B). (Box 15)
    - -Academic disciplines. Political science (VI-D). (Box 15)
    - -Academic disciplines. Religion (VI-C). (Box 15)
    - -Advertising with Western motifs (not listed on cards) (VIII-Other). (Box 15)
    - -Facts. Chinese in the West (V-5). (Box 15)
    - -Facts. Cowboys and raching, old time (V-B). (Box 15)
    - -Facts. Newspapers in the West (V-R). (Box 15)
    - -Literary. Booksellers' information (IV-I). (Box 16)
    - -Literary. Isolated subjects within Western fiction (IV-E). (Box 16)
    - -Literary. Songs and poems (cowboys). IV-H. (Box 16)
    - -Ledger. (Box 16)
    - -National Foundatin on the Arts and Humanities (NFAH)., September 1969. (Box 16)
    - -Correspondence. (Box 16)
    - -Ev's notes (Everett Jones). (Box 16)
    - -Phil's notes (Philip Durham). (Box 16)
    - -M. (Box 16)
    - -P-Q. (Box 16)
    - -Salinas Rodeo, Notes and miscellaneous., 1965. (Box 16)
    - -Durham, Philip. Jay Gatsby and Hopalong Cassidy. Reprint from Themes and Directions in American Literature., pp.163-170. (Box 16)
    - -Durham, Philip, and Jones, Everett. Letter to Los Angeles Times., November 21, 1968.; 3 leaves. Typescript (photocopy). (Box 16)
    - -Checklist (Western myth). (Box 16)
    - -Notes re myth. (Box 16)
    - -Cowboys/westerns. (Box 16)
    - -Notebook. Articles and clippings re Westerns. (Box 16)
    - -Research material. Various articles on Western life., Photocopies. 3 folders. (Box 17)
    - -Card index re articles on Western life., Stored in green box. (Box 17)